A Guide to the Papers of James Fenimore Cooper, 1813-1844 and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Collection of James Fenimore Cooper, 1813-1844 and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6245-a
This collection consists of ca. 130 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must use the microfilm of The Pathfinder manuscript unless permission to use the original is obtained from senior Special Collections staff.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited on 1960 April 16 and made a gift on July 1, 1991.
Scope and Content Information
The bulk of the collection is dated 1813-1850 and consists of correspondence with literary agents, publishers, friends, business associates, historians, and literary figures, relating to Cooper's career, legal and financial affairs, travels in Europe, family, and social life; manuscripts for The Pathfinder (1840), The Two Admirals (1842), and Mercedes of Castile (1840), partial manuscripts for The History of the Navy of the United States of America (1839), The Pilot (1823), Afloat and Ashore (1844), and The Water Witch (1831), and printer's manuscript for Home As Found (1838) with holograph corrections by Cooper; legal documents relating to Cooper's libel suit against James Watson Webb and to his land holdings in New York; correspondence of Cooper's daughter, Susan Fenimore Cooper, chiefly with William Branford Shubrick, relating to her father's death, his religious beliefs, and Cooper family genealogy; book reviews, prints, and engravings.
Cooper's correspondents include William Cullen Bryant, Richard Henry Dana, Rufus Wilmot Griswold, Jay family, and William Gilmore Simms. Susan Cooper's correspondents include Felix Octavius Darley, George Washington Greene, and Charles Mathews. Many of the letters have been published in The Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, edited by James F. Beard (1960).
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - Article (in French) on Cooper by George Sand., 58 p.
  - Title page The Chainbearer., 1 p.
  - Four sketches by Bensell for The Deerslayer., 4 p.
  - Four engravings of Cooper., Grey Box 1
  - Leaf of The Headsman.
  - Fragments of The Headsman., 4 sheets
  - Preliminary draft of a report ("The Races") written for the New York Patriot., 1 sheet
  - Carey and Lea printed leaflet, 1 p., for (and some miscellaneous Ms booksellers' documents) Last of the Mohicans., 7 items
  - Preface to The Chain-bearer, or, The Littlepage manuscripts, 2 p.
- Miscellaneous
  - Various notes concerning Cooper's novels, 18 handwritten leaves, 3 typed leaves
  - Typescript and photostats of 1850 preface to the collected Leather-Stocking Tales., 2 p. each
  - Typescript and photostat of introduction to the Spiller and Blackburn Bibliography., 1 p. each
  - The Wept of the Wish-Ton-Wish. Title page of the first printed edition, Florence, 1829. Biblioteca Nationale, Florence., 1 p. (photocopy)
  - Carte dressee pour la lecture du Pilote Roman de J. Fenimore Cooper, par A. M. Perrot [1824?], 1 p.
  - Page of Introduction to Naval History (The History of the Navy of the United States of America)., 1 sheet, AMs
  - Fragment of manuscript on England - Notions of Americans., 1 p.
  - Page from Oak Openings., 1 p.
  - Page from Oak Openings, Chapter XX dealing with Indians., 1 p.
  - Fragment of page from Oak Openings
  - Fragment of page from Oak Openings
  - Postage Stamps - 5, 2c
  - Preface for revised Bentley edition of The Red Rover., 2 p.
  - Page from Satanstoe, or The Little Page Manuscript
  - Page from Sea Lions., 1 p., Ch.VI
  - The Spy, Printed Theatre Program, Philadelphia Theatre on December 11, 1823.
  - Parts of 2 pages with corrections, Regarding Admirals in the United States Navy.
  - Pages from The Water Witch, 2 p.
  - Part of the original manuscript of The Water Witch
    comprises chapters 12, 13, and 14 (pp. 144-186 of volume I, 1831) and chapters 10, 16 (pp. 138-251 of volume II.), ca. 150 pages (in the hand of an amanuensis but filled with Cooper's autograph corrections and revisions)
  - Original manuscript of Two Admirals., 257 p.
    Bound blue volume, Barrett Room
  - Manuscript of the novel Mercedes of Castile. Ca. 1853, 268 p. Bound blue volume
  - Original Manuscript of Afloat and Ashore., 6 p.
  - Original manuscript of Chapter 24 Afloat and Ashore., 13 p.
  - Framed portrait of Cooper in oil by Winlker.
  - Framed miniature portrait of Cooper by W. H. Powell.
- Letters
  - Cooper to William Jay, [Re death of daughter] 1813 Aug 29, ALS. 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. 1, (page 29).
  - Mrs. (Mary A.) Isaac Cooper to Mrs. Banyer [Re death of Isaac Cooper] 1818 Mar 10, ALS. 2 p.
  - Cooper to L. Bradish [Re planned visit and meeting] 1820 Feb 9, ALS.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 38).
  - Cooper to General Peter Gansevoort [Re politics] 1820 Apr 19, ALS. 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 39).
  - Cooper to Captain Shubrick [Re Cooper's review of naval history in Scientific & Literary Reportage. Was something of Cooper's appearing there?] 1821 May 23, ALS. 1 p., w/env.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 68).
  - Cooper to Chief Justice John Jay [Re politics] 1821 Sep 6, ALS. 1 p. w/env.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 70).
  - Chief Justice John Jay to Cooper [Re politics] 1821 Sep 10, AL. 1 p.
  - Cooper (in Paris) to Mrs. Peter A. Jay [Long, gossipy letter on Parisian society, with some literary remarks.] 1826 [Oct 1-15?], ALS. 4 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 158).
  - Cooper (in Paris) to Mrs. Peter A. Jay [More gossip re Paris. Mentions Lafayette. Includes drawing of LaGrange] 1827 Mar 26, ALS. 4 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 200).
  - Cooper to [Francis] Moore [Re Rover and other publications.] [1827?] [1821], ALS. 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 228).
  - Cooper to [Hector] Bossange (his French publisher) [Re Rover. Has slip with dates of publication.] 1827 Nov [15-27?], ALS. 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 239).
  - Cooper to Charles Gosselin [A short note re Rover .] 1827 [Nov 19-24?], ALS. 1 p.
  - Cooper to Henry George Grey, Viscount Howick 1828 [Mar?], ALS. [Not printed in Letters]
  - Cooper to Mrs. Alexander Baring [1828 Mar 30], ALS. 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 260).
  - Cooper to Lord Howick [Re Navy.] [ca.1828 Apr], ALS. 2 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 255).
  - Cooper to Mrs. Peter A. Jay [Gossip re English aristocrats.], 2 p. [1829?] [Jan?], AL.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 353).
  - Signed draft agreement with Walther [1830 May 26], 1 p. Contract for Water Witch.
  - Cooper to F. Alph. de Syon [Invitation to tour Swiss Saxony. In French.] [1830 Jun], ALS. 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 417).
  - Cooper to George Gallagher & Co. 1830 Jul 28, ALS. 2 p.
  - Cooper to Charles King for the New York American [Re Greenough's sculpture of the 2 cherubs.] 1830 Jul 29, ALS. 1 l. Above 2 ALS.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 431).
  - Cooper to Mr. Gosselin Re business. ca.1830, ALS. 1 p.
    This letter is not printed in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper.
  - Cooper to James Postelt Jervey 1831 Apr 10, ALS. 1 p. Invitation.
    Regrets.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. II, (page 67).
  - Cooper to Mrs. Peter Jay 1831 Jun 16, ALS. 4 p.
    Comments on Water Witch pp.109-110, and literary popularity. Reflections on Americans in Europe and his wish that his daughters not marry abroad. Good letter.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. II, (page 102).
  - Cooper to Colburn and Bentley 1831 Jul 2, ALS. 1 p.
    Literary matters. Comments re The Bravo. Mentions Spy and Pilot.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. II, (page 115).
  - Cooper to David Bailie Warden [1831 Aug 15?], ALS, 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. II, (page 135).
  - Cooper to Colburn and Bentley 1831 Aug 29, ALS. 1 p. Fragment.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. I, (page 136-137, last par. only).
  - Cooper to Vis. Chas. E. H. Dambray [Scandal re Friend's daughter's elopement.] 1831 Dec 3, ALS. 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. II, (page 161).
  - Cooper to Baron Camille de Varaigne du Bourg [Re Mrs. Cooper's health.] [1831-32?], ALS.
    Missing 3/27/68.
  - Cooper to Samuel G. Howe [Re cholera epidemic.] 1832 Apr 12, ALS. 1 p.
  - Cooper to Lombard, Odier and Co. 1832 Sep 5, ALS.
    In French. Sending letter of credit.
  - Cooper to Pierre Alexandre Adolphe Jullien 1832 Nov 30, ALS.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. II, (page 365).
  - Cooper to an unidentified friend [1832-33?], AL. Fragment. 1 p.
  - Cooper to Henry L. Webb [1833 Apr?], AL. Invitation. 1 p.
  - Cooper to Mr. Bentley [Requesting sheets for The Headsman .] [1833 Jul?], AL, 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. II, (page 396).
  - Cooper to Peter A. Jay [Re Mrs. Cooper's financial affairs.] [1833 Nov 20], ALS. 1 p.
  - Cooper to Dr. Matthews [1835] Jan 19, ALS. 1 p. Invitation.
  - Cooper to J. B. Longacre [Re Polish refugees in U.S.] 1837 May 28, ALS. 1 p.
  - Cooper to John C. Jay [Re the latter's wedding.] 1837 Jun 16, ALS. 1 p.
  - Cooper to Cary, Lea and Blanchard [Instructing them to send sheets of Homeward Bound to him.] 1838 May 23, ALS. 1 p.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. III, (page 325).
  - Cooper to James de Peyster Ogden 1839 Jul 8, ALS. 1 p.
    Financial affairs.
  - Cooper to J. D. P. Ogden 1840 Jan 14, ALS. 2 typescript copies. 1 p.
    Financial affairs. Refers to contract with Lea & Co. for 2 books which are already printed but not yet issued because of hard times.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 10).
  - Cooper to Mrs. William Heath-cote de Lancey 1840 May 15, ALS. 1 p.
    Trip to N.Y.C.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 40).
  - Cooper to Joseph Ingersoll 1840 Jun 5, ALS. 1 p.
    Re plans for latter's trip to Cooperstown.
  - (Closing) Cooper to [John A.]Dix [1840 Dec 15-16?], ALS. Photo of Cooper by Brady. Fragment.
  - Cooper to George Roberts 1841 Jan 22, ALS. 2 p.
    Literary, re Imagination and Heart.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 110).
  - Cooper to J. deP. Ogden 1841 Jan 31, ALS. 1 p.
    Political views; comments re Whigs and Webster, and court battles (personal).
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 113).
  - Cooper to Webb and Douglas 1841 May 14, ALS. 1 p.
    Re account.
  - Cooper to Richard H. Dana, Sr. [1841 Oct 15], ALS. 1 p.
    Social.
  - Cooper to J. Tomlin 1841 Nov 8, ALS. A Tenn. 1 p. postmaster.
    Sending autograph; but mentions Mohicans, Prairie, Pathfinder, and Deerslayer.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 188).
  - Cooper to Thomas Baldwin 1841 Nov 24, ALS. 2 p.
    Literary, re Gleanings and the disadvantages of being a writer in U.S. Good letter.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 194).
  - Cooper to David Low 1842 Apr 17, ALS. 1 p.
    Legal matter.
  - Cooper to John L. O'Sullivan 1842 Apr 29, ALS. 1 p.
    Re articles on naval history. Opinion against biographies of living men. Portraits.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 285).
  - Cooper to William Cullen Bryant 1842 Jun 29 [28], ALS. 1 p.
    Reviews Naval History litigation. Possibly good letter to show example of J. F. C.'s legal tangles.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 297).
  - Cooper to J. de P. Ogden [ca.1842 Jun], ALS. 1 p.
    Recommendation for naval duty.
  - Cooper to [J. G. Jarvis, Jr.] 1842 Aug 7, ALS. 1 p.
    Autograph.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 308).
  - Cooper to T. W. [Failer] Fields 1842 Aug 17, ALS. 1 p.
    Re Deerslayer characters of Judith and Hetty. Good letter.
  - Cooper to Charles J. Ingersoll 1842 Nov 7, ALS. 1 p.
    Recommendation for a minister.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 320).
  - Cooper to R. W. Griswold(editor of Graham's Magazine ) 1842 Nov 26, ALS. 1 p.
    Re publication of "Autobiography of a Pocket Handker- chief" and "Oliver Hazard Perry."
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 321).
  - Cooper to Mrs. Banyer 1843 Feb 27, ALS. 2 p.
    Beautiful letter of condolence on the death of her brother, Peter Augustus Jay. Reflections on friendship and death.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 363).
  - Cooper to H. E. Parker 1843 May 27, ALS. 1 p. Typescript copy.
    Autograph. Re spelling of the name "Fenimore" and its provenance.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 384).
  - Cooper to John H. Sherburne 1843 May 28, ALS. 1 p.
    Declining to deliver the eulogy for Commodore David Porter.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 385).
  - 1843 Jun 25 Cooper to [Horatio] Greenough, ALS. 1 p.
    Funny. Re Greenough's naked statue of Washington. The mediocrity of American public opinion.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 389).
  - Cooper to W. G. Simms 1844 Jan 5, ALS. 2 p.
    Vituperative letter about all his literary and personal woes. The decline of his career since Notions of the Americans.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 436).
  - Cooper to Richard Bentley(London publisher) 1844 Jan 9, ALS
    Literary-financial. Miles Wallingford and Ned Myers.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 440).
  - Cooper to W. G. Simms 1844 Apr 22, ALS. 2 p.
  - Cooper to Wiley and Putnam 1844 Sep 29, ALS.
    Afloat and Ashore conclusion ready to be announced. 3 lines only.
    This item is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper vol. IV, (page 480).